Kaiyang Zhou

Research Fellow School of Computer Science and Engineering Nanyang Technological University, Singapore

E-mail: kaiyang.zhou@ntu.edu.sg | Homepage | Google Scholar | Github

Research Interests

Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Artificial Intelligence

Research Highlights

My research revolves around the development of *generalizable* (across changing data distributions) and *efficient* (small / fast / low-power) machine learning models—particularly those based on deep learning—for large-scale data analytics, with applications to computer vision, reinforcement learning, medical image analysis, speech recognition, and more. My papers have been published at major journals and conferences in relevant fields, such as <u>Trans. PAMI</u> (flagship journal in AI with IF = 24.31), <u>IJCV</u> (flagship journal in computer vision with IF = 13.37), ICLR (#1 conference in AI), and the three prominent computer vision conferences (i.e., CVPR, ICCV & ECCV). I have been actively engaging in academic services: I am a *guest editor* of IJCV and an *area chair/senior program committee member* for BMVC'22 and AAAI'23.

Google Scholar Citations: 2,500 citations with h-index 15 (as of Jan 2023).

Appointments

Nanyang Technological University, Singapore Research Fellow with Prof. Ziwei Liu and Prof. Chen Change Loy	Jan 2021 – now
Samsung AI Center Cambridge, UK Research Intern with Prof. Tao Xiang	Nov 2018 – May 2019
SIAT-MMLAB, Chinese Academy of Sciences, China Research Assistant with Prof. Yu Qiao	Oct 2016 – Aug 2017

Education

PhD in Computer Science, University of Surrey, UK	2020
Supervised by Prof. Tao Xiang	
MSc in Advanced Computing (Distinction), University of Bristol, UK Supervised by Prof. Majid Mirmehdi and Dr. Adeline Paiement	2016
BSc in Computer Science (First Class Honor), University of Ulster, UK Supervised by Dr. Inaki Rano	2015

Publications

Journal impact factors:

IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI): 24.31 International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV): 13.37 IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP): 11.04

Top-3 publications:

<u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Ziwei Liu, Yu Qiao, Tao Xiang, and Chen Change Loy. Domain generalization: A survey. *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)*, 2022. **IF: 24.31**. (TL;DR: A comprehensive survey that summarizes the recent ten-year progress in domain generalization.)

- <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Jingkang Yang, Chen Change Loy, and Ziwei Liu. Learning to prompt for vision-language models. *International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)*, 130:2337–2348, 2022. IF: 13.37. (TL;DR: An efficient and generalizable prompt learning approach for adapting large-scale vision-language models.)
- 3. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Andrea Cavallaro, and Tao Xiang. Learning generalisable omni-scale representations for person re-identification. *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)*, 2021. **IF: 24.31**.
 - (TL;DR: An extremely lightweight person re-id neural network that, once trained, can generalize from one dataset to another without retraining (also widely used by the community for other human-centered applications such as person tracking and human behavior analysis).)

Refereed journal articles:

- 1. Yuhang Zang, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Chen Huang, and Chen Change Loy. Semi-supervised and long-tailed object detection with cascadematch. *International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)*, 2023.
- 2. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Ziwei Liu, Yu Qiao, Tao Xiang, and Chen Change Loy. Domain generalization: A survey. *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)*, 2022.
- 3. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Jingkang Yang, Chen Change Loy, and Ziwei Liu. Learning to prompt for vision-language models. *International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)*, 130:2337–2348, 2022.
- 4. Zhongying Deng, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Da Li, Junjun He, Yi-Zhe Song, and Tao Xiang. Dynamic instance domain adaptation. *IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP)*, 31:4585–4597, 2022.
- 5. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Yu Qiao, and Tao Xiang. Domain adaptive ensemble learning. *IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP)*, 30:8008–8018, 2021.
- 6. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Andrea Cavallaro, and Tao Xiang. Learning generalisable omni-scale representations for person re-identification. *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)*, 2021.

Refereed conference papers:

- 1. Tingwei Wang, Da Li, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Tao Xiang, and Yi-Zhe Song. Learning to augment via implicit differentiation for domain generalization. In *British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)*, 2022. **Oral**.
- Jingkang Yang, Pengyun Wang, Dejian Zou, Zitang Zhou, Kunyuan Ding, Wenxuan Peng, Haoqi Wang, Guangyao Chen, Bo Li, Yiyou Sun, Xuefeng Du, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Wayne Zhang, Dan Hendrycks, Yixuan Li, and Ziwei Liu. Openood: Benchmarking generalized out-of-distribution detection. In *Proceedings* of the Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Track on Datasets and Benchmarks, 2022.
- 3. Jingkang Yang, Yi Zhe Ang, Zujin Guo, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Wayne Zhang, and Ziwei Liu. Panoptic scene graph generation. In *European conference on computer vision (ECCV)*. Springer, 2022.
- 4. Yuhang Zang, Wei Li, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Chen Huang, and Chen Change Loy. Open-vocabulary detr with conditional matching. In *European conference on computer vision (ECCV)*. Springer, 2022. **Oral**, 158/5,803=2.7%.
- 5. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Jingkang Yang, Chen Change Loy, and Ziwei Liu. Conditional prompt learning for vision-language models. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, pages 16816–16825, 2022.
- 6. Zhongying Deng, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, and Tao Xiang. Domain attention consistency for multi-source domain adaptation. In *British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)*, 2021.
- 7. Yezhen Wang, Bo Li, Tong Che, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Ziwei Liu, and Dongsheng Li. Energy-based openworld uncertainty modeling for confidence calibration. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)*, pages 9302–9311, 2021.
- 8. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Yu Qiao, and Tao Xiang. Domain generalization with mixstyle. In *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*, 2021.
- 9. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Timothy Hospedales, and Tao Xiang. Learning to generate novel domains for domain generalization. In *European conference on computer vision (ECCV)*, volume 12361, pages 561–578. Springer, 2020.

- 10. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Timothy Hospedales, and Tao Xiang. Deep domain-adversarial image generation for domain generalisation. In *Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)*, volume 34, pages 13025–13032, 2020.
- 11. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Andrea Cavallaro, and Tao Xiang. Omni-scale feature learning for person re-identification. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)*, pages 3702–3712, 2019.
- 12. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Tao Xiang, and Andrea Cavallaro. Video summarisation by classification with deep reinforcement learning. In *British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)*, 2018. **Oral**, 37/862=4.3%.
- 13. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yu Qiao, and Tao Xiang. Deep reinforcement learning for unsupervised video summarization with diversity-representativeness reward. In *Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)*, volume 32, 2018. **Oral, 418/3,800=11%**.
- 14. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Adeline Paiement, and Majid Mirmehdi. Detecting humans in rgb-d data with cnns. In 2017 Fifteenth IAPR International Conference on Machine Vision Applications (MVA), pages 306–309. IEEE, 2017.

Workshop papers and preprints:

- 1. Yuhang Zang, Wei Li, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Chen Huang, and Chen Change Loy. Unified vision and language prompt learning. *arXiv preprint arXiv:2210.07225*, 2022.
- 2. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yuanhan Zhang, Yuhang Zang, Jingkang Yang, Chen Change Loy, and Ziwei Liu. Ondevice domain generalization. *arXiv preprint arXiv:2209.07521*, 2022.
- 3. Yuanhan Zhang, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, and Ziwei Liu. Neural prompt search. *arXiv preprint arXiv*:2206.04673, 2022.
- 4. Jingkang Yang, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, and Ziwei Liu. Full-spectrum out-of-distribution detection. *arXiv* preprint arXiv:2204.05306, 2022.
- 5. Jingkang Yang, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yixuan Li, and Ziwei Liu. Generalized out-of-distribution detection: A survey. *arXiv preprint arXiv:2110.11334*, 2021.
- 6. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Yu Qiao, and Tao Xiang. Mixstyle neural networks for domain generalization and adaptation. *arXiv preprint arXiv:2107.02053*, 2021.
- 7. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Chen Change Loy, and Ziwei Liu. Semi-supervised domain generalization with stochastic stylematch. In *NeurIPS 2021 Workshop on Distribution Shifts: Connecting Methods and Applications*, 2021.
- 8. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u> and Tao Xiang. Torchreid: A library for deep learning person re-identification in pytorch. *arXiv preprint arXiv:1910.10093*, 2019.

Theses:

- 1. Kaiyang Zhou. *Adaptation and Generalization Across Domains in Visual Recognition with Deep Neural Networks*. PhD thesis, University of Surrey, 2020. pdf
- 2. Kaiyang Zhou. *Human Detection with Convolutional Neural Networks in RGB-D Images*. MSc thesis, University of Bristol, 2016. (Best Master's Thesis.)
- 3. Kaiyang Zhou. *Computer Vision-based Local Navigation for Mobile Robots*. BSc thesis, Ulster University, 2015.

Patents

- 1. "Dynamic prompt generation technology for vision-language models," filed through NTU & Sense-Time, Singapore Patent No. 10202202104P, 2022; China Patent No. 202210431968.4, 2022.
- 2. "Deep learning-based video summarization method, device and end equipment," filed through SIAT, China Patent No. CN201711374076.0, 2018.

Grants

Co-I, "3D Geometry	and Semantic	Modeling for	or Human-Scene	Interaction,"	MOE Acre	Tier 2. (S\$
613,574.00.)						

Professional Services

Professional Services	
Guest Editor International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)	2023
Area Chair / Senior Program Committee AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI) British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)	2023 2022
Organizer / Co-Organizer ECCV 2022 Computer Vision in the Wild Challenges The AI Talks (an initiative aiming to democratize AI through open talks)	2022 2022
Reviewer IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI) IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP) IEEE Transactions on Multimedia (TMM) IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology (TCSVT) International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV) ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications, and Applications International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI) IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV) British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)	s (TOMM)
Teaching	
Lecturer / Guest Lecturer, Nanyang Technological University Open-World Visual Recognition (AI6126: Advanced Computer Vision) Object Detection (OpenMMLab Workshop)	Apr 2022 June 2021
Teaching Assistant , Queen Mary University of London <i>ECS797: Machine Learning for Visual Data Analytics ECS708: Machine Learning</i>	Spring 2018 Fall 2017, Fall 2018
Mentoring	
Yuanhan Zhang (PhD@NTU) Yuhang Zang (PhD@NTU) Jingkang Yang (PhD@NTU) Zhongying Deng (PhD@Surrey)	2022 – now 2021 – now 2021 – now 2019 – 2020
Talks	
Nanyang Technological University Towards generalizable and efficient learning system designs	Feb 2023
National University of Singapore Towards generalizable and efficient learning system designs	Jan 2023

Oct 2021

Nanyang Technological University, IET CV Workshop

Visual recognition: From closed-set discrete labels to open-set natural language supervision

University of Surrey, Centre for Vision, Speech and Signal Processing (CVSSP)

Adaptation and generalization across domains in visual recognition with deep neural networks

Nanyang Technological University, MMLab

Multi-source domain generalization and adaptation

Queen Mary University of London, Intelligent Sensing Summer School

Aug 2018

Summarizing videos with deep reinforcement learning

Honors & Awards

Outstanding Reviewer, <u>ECCV 2022</u>	2022
Outstanding Reviewer, <u>ICCV 2021</u>	2021
Top 25% of Program Committee Members, <u>AAAI 2021</u>	2021
University Strategic Funds Studentship, University of Surrey	2019
Queen Mary Principal's Research Studentship, Queen Mary University of London	2017
Innovation Scholarship (for contribution to patent), SIAT Chinese Academy of Sciences	2017
Best Master's Thesis, University of Bristol CS Department	2016

Selected Open-Source Software

I promote open-source AI research and have been an activate contributor to the open-source community on Github. I have developed several open-source projects widely used by the community of both academia and industry (with over 6k stars received in total on Github). Below are the two most representative projects. See my Github page for more.

1. Torchreid

- a well-documented Python library for research on deep learning-based person re-identification
- provides a model zoo containing various pre-trained models
- receives 3.7k+ stars on Github (ranked No. 1 by popularity on Github for person re-id)
- link: github.com/KaiyangZhou/deep-person-reid

2. Dassl.pytorch

- a Python library for research on domain generalization and domain adaptation
- receives 700+ stars on Github
- link: github.com/KaiyangZhou/Dassl.pytorch

Last update: January 2023